<teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
  <titleStmt>
   <title>
    [Original Title]- electronic transcription
   </title>
   <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
   <principal>J. Gerald Kennedy</principal>
  </titleStmt>
  <publicationStmt>
     <publisher>Louisiana State University</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Baton Rouge, LA</pubPlace>
     <date>2014</date>
  </publicationStmt>
  <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>Southern Literary Messenger, vol12, 1835</bibl>
  </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
          <div>
              <ab>
                <pb n="1"/>
                 SOUTHERN LITERARY MESSENGER.
                 VÂ°â-- H- RICHMOND, DECEMBER, 1835. No. 1.
                 T.
                 W- WHITE, Pnopmmron.
                 
                 PUBLISHERâS NOTICE.
                 [CP The gentleman, referred to in the ninth number
                 ?:e:1hÂ¢ Messenger, as filling its editorial chair, retired
                 68 with the eleventh number; and the intellectual
                 of the lint of the paper is now under the conduct
                 guishedlwprletor, assisted by a gentleman of distin-
                 in the h lterary talents. Thus seconded, he is S!'tl'lg\lll"|8
                 present OPS of rendering the second volume which the
                 .up t Number commences, at least as deserving of
                 tokgsr RS. the former was: nay, if he reads artght the
                 even S_\\;lh\ch are given him .of the future, it teems with
                 hitherlgi Ct* banquets for his readers, than they have
                 so efljoyed at his board. _
                 ceivegle of the contributors, whose ef'fusions.have re-
                 (whal _lbe largest share of praise from critics, and
                 by thas better still) have been read with most pleasure
                 for re arger, unsophlsticated class, whom Sterne loved
                 and adlflg, and being pleased âthey knew not why,
                 theirczfe Ytot whereforeâ-may be expected to continue
                 for si avers. Among these, we hope to be pardoned
                 with lzigllflg out the name of l."1.l'..EDGAR   Poe; not
                 been esign to make any mvidious distinction, but
                 demllfo such a mention of him finds numberless prece-
                 ,he 'll the Journals on every side, which have rung
                 andPl`:lses of his uniquely original vein of unagmation,
                 rumÂ°d_b\1morous,_dehcate satire, We wish that deco-
                 whichld not forbid our specifying other names also,
                 or," Would afford ample guarantee for the fulfilment
                 our (sir promises than ours: but it may not be; and of
                 fruits er contributors, all we can say is-â by their
                 It iY8 Shall know them.â _ _ .
                 comming part of ourpresent plan, to insert all original
                 word. Jcations as editorial ; that is, simply to omit the
                 head f For the. Southern Literary Messengerâ at the
                 peeing Such articles :-unless the contributor shall es-
                 lomethyf desire. to havethat caption prefixed, or there. be
                 itself log which requiresit in the nature of the article
                 prim; Selected artzcles,.of course, will bear some appro-
                 W_ tokgfl of_their origin.
                 ghd alll tlns brief salutation to patrons and readers, We
                 year P fwrselves for entering upon the work of another
                 t, Â» With zeal and energy increased, by the recollec-
                 Â°;Â°;Â°f kindness, and by the hopes of still greater suc-
                 dÂ°Partm
                 , -.ii-11-Li-ll
                 SKETCHES OF THE HISTORY
                 PRESENT countries or 'ra|Po1.i, wrru som: Ac-
                 Â°0UN'rs or -rm; ornsa autnaar srarns.
                 âND
                 NO. IX.-(Contlnued.)
                 ,`AbÂ°\1l- this period commenced those differences be-
                 to 2: Fmhoe and the Algerine Government, which led
                 the Fflverthrow of the latter, and the establishment of
                 ~h,ch'Â°Â°âÂ¢ll_in Northern Africa; the circumstances
                 Nd Â°Â¢Â¢astoned the dispute were however of much
                 Â°' date.
                 |Â°&amp;""Â°Â°â |793 and 1798 the French Government on
                 ml Occasions obtained from the Dey and merchants
                 FIVE DOLLARS PER ANNUM.
                 ____. 
                 of Algiers, large quantities of grain on credit, for the
                 subsistence of its armies in Italy, and the supply of the
                 Southern Department where a great scarcity then pre-
                 vailed. The creditors endeavored to have their claims
                 on this account satisfied by the Directory, but that in-
                 capable and rapacious Government had neither the
                 principle to admit, nor the ability to discharge such de-
                 mands; every species of chicanery was in consequence
                 employed by it in evading them, until the rupture with
                 Turkey produced by the expedition to Egypt placing
                 the Barbary States either really or apparently at war
                 with the French Republic, a pretext was thus afforded
                 for deferring their settlement indefinitely. Under the
                 Consular regime however, a treaty of peace was con-
                 cluded with Algiers on the 17th of December 1801,
                 by the thirteenth article of which, the Government
                 of each State engaged to cause payment to be made
                 of all debts due by itself or its subjects to the Gov-
                 ernment or subjects of the other; the former political
                 and commercial relations between the two countries
                 were re-established, and the Dey restored to France
                 the territories and privileges called the ./Qfricafn Con-
                 cessions, which had been seized by him on the break-
                 ing out of the war. This treaty was ratified by the
                 Dey on the 5th of April l802, and after examination
                 of the claims on both sides, the French Govern-
                 ment acknowledged itself debtor for a large amount to
                 the Jewish mercantile house of Bacri and Busnach of
                 Algiers, as representing the African creditors. Of the
                 sum thus acknowledged to be due, only a very small
                 portion was paid, and the Dey Hadji Ali seeing no
                 other means of obtaining the remainder, in 1809 seized
                 upon the Concessions ; they were however of little value
                 to France at that time, when her flag was never seen in
                 the Mediterranean, and their confiscation merely served
                 as a pretext for withholding farther payment. In 1813,
                 when the star of Napoleon began to wane, and he
                 found it necessary to assume at least the appearance of
                 honesty, he declared that measures would be taken for
                 the adjustment of the Algerine claims; but he fell
                 without redeeming his promise, and on the distribution
                 of his spoils, the Jewish merchants had not interest
                 enough to obtain their rightful portion, which amounted
                 to fourteen millions of francs.
                 Upon the return of the Bourbons to the throne of
                 France, the government of that country became desirous
                 turenew its former intercourse with the Barbary States,
                 and to regain its ancient establishments and privileges
                 in their territories, which were considered important
                 from political as well as commercial motives. For this
                 purpose, M. Deval a person who was educated in the
                 East and had been long attached to the French Em-
                 bassy at Constantinople, was appointed Consul General
                 of France in Barbary, and sent to Algiers with powers
                 to negotiate. The first result of this mission, was a
                 convention which has never been officially published;
                 however in consequence of it the ./Ifricau Concessions
                 were restored to France, together with the exclusive
                 right of fishing for coral on the coasts in their vicinity
                 Vol.. II.-1
              <pb n="2"/>
                2 SOUTHERN LITERARY MESSENGER. ,e
                and various commercial privileges; in return for which
                the French were to pay annually to Algiers, the sum
                of sixty thousand francs. It appears also to have
                been understood between the parties, that no fortifi-
                cations were to be erected within the ceded territories
                in addition to those already standing, and that ar-
                rangements should be speedily made for the examina-
                tion and settlement of all their claims on both sides,
                not only of those for which provision was made in the
                treaty of 1801, but also of such as were founded on
                subsequent occurrences; after this mutual adjustment
                the treaty of 1801 confirming all former treaties was to
                be in force.
                The annual sum required by Omar for the Conces.
                sions, was much greater than any which had been pre.
                viously paid for them by France; Hussein however
                immediately on his elevation to the throne, raised it to
                two hundred thousand francs, and he moreover declared,
                that the debt acknowledged to be due to his subjects
                must be paid, before any notice were taken of claims
                which were still liable to be contested. In opposition
                to these demands, the French endeavored to prove their
                right to the territories of Calle and Bastion de France
                by reference to ancient treaties both with Algiers and
                the Porte, in which no mention is made of payment for
                them; with regard to the claims, they insisted that the
                only just mode of settlement, was by admitting into one
                statement all the demands which could be established
                on either side, and then balancing the account. The
                Dey however remained firm in his resolution, and ex-
                hibited signs of preparation to expel the French from
                the Concessions, when their government yielded the
                point concerning the amount to be annnually paid.
                A compromise was made respecting the claims be.
                tween the French Government and the Agents of the
                Algerines, on the 28th of October, 1819; as the ar-
                ticles of this agreement have never been published,
                its terms are only to be gathered from the decla.
                rations of the French Ministers in the Legislative
                Chambers, and the semi-ofiicial communications in the
                Jlfonltettr the organ of the Government. From thegg it
                appears that the French Government acknowledged ig.
                self indebted for the sum of seven millions of francs, to
                Messrs. Bacrt and Busnach, which was to be received
                by them in full discharge of claims on the
                _ _ part of Al-
                giers, under the thirteenth article of the treaty of 1801 °
                from this sum however was to be retained a sufiiciency
                to cover the demands of French subjects against Algiers
                under the same article, which demands were to be sub-
                stantiated by the Courts of Law of France ; finally
                each party was to settle the claims of its own subjea;
                against the other, founded on occurrences eub,¢q,,em_
                to the conclusion of the said treaty. The French ms.
                torical writers affect to consider this arrangement en-
                tirely as a private affair between their Government and
                the Jewish merchants, and indeed the Ministry eww,
                vored at it-st to represent it in that light to the Legs,
                llwni bm they were forced to abandon this ground
                when they communicated its stipulations, and the M;,,_
                ister of Foreign Aiihirs declared in the Chamber of
                Deputies, that the Dey had formally accepted it on the
                12th of April 1820, and had admitted that the ltgggy of
                1801 was thereby fully executed,
                In order to comply with this arrangement, a bill rc-
                quiring an appropriation of seven millions of francs Wu
                \»
                in June, 1820, submitted by the French Ministry £0 Legislative Chambers, in both of which its ad0P _
                was resisted by the small minority then opposed I-0 0 l
                Government. The debates on this occasion are W  "`
                of notice, as many of the arguments advanced 8  *
                the appropriation, have been since employed to d 
                the bill for executing the treaty of 1831 by which _ v
                United States were to be indemnified for the 10 _ e
                indicted on their commerce by Napoleon. The ' ,
                against France were in both cases pronounced tml'  ' ' ~
                and obsolete [victlles reclamations, créances dechudl '  
                the fact that they had long remained unsettled, *-
                thus deemed suflicient to authorize their indefinite ~ ' _
                ponement. The great diminution to which the  
                tors had assented, was considered as affording 8 " _
                presumption that their demands were destitute Of " '
                dation; and the probability that many of the cl  "  
                had been purchased at a low price by the actual ' ' '
                ers, from the persons with whom the contract!  
                originally made, was gravely alleged as a rea80" " if
                not satisfying them. The advantages secured t0  
                by each Convention were examined in detail,atlfl  
                pared with the sums required for extinguishlnl  
                debts; and the Ministry were in both cases cens\ll`°d i
                not having obtained more in return for their pnymdlf
                It is not surprising to hear such sentiments avoid'
                men educated in the service of Napoleon, b\1l~_i‘ t
                painful to find them supported by others distin _ l
                for their literary merits, and for their exertion8 In ___
                cause ofliberty. ' _ ,"'i7
                The bill for the appropriation of the seven mlm*
                of francs, was passed by a large majority in both C
                bers, the influence of the Crown being at that ._ A
                overwhelming. Four millions and a half were in  
                sequence paid within the ensuing three year!  
                Jewish merchants, who having thus received th0 '  
                amount of their own demands retired to ltalY5  
                remaining two and a half millions were retained W  
                Government of France in order to secure the dl|°h 5
                of the claims of its subjects, under the treaty da* ,
                which were yet pending in the Courts of th0 dl
                dom. At the retention of this sum, the Dey#  
                affected to be at first much surprised, and he  
                that the Government should hasten the decision!  
                Courts; however as years passed by without BUY    
                of approach to a definitive settlement, his  
                became uncontrollable. Moreover in addition  
                annoyance occasioned by this constant p08lP‘?"¢   2
                he was much dissatisfied, on account of the fort\5°'  
                which the French were erecting at Calle, 00”";?dj
                he insisted to the understanding between Ulf  
                at the time of its cession. To his observ8U:'_:'|l
                inquiries on both these subjects he receivdi "dp
                from the French Consul which were genera||Y ° 
                and often insulting, until at length wearied |91 ' "*
                and having strong reason to believe that M- _ __ _
                personal interest in creating obstacles to B11 "dlp f
                of the difficulties, he determined to addrell ill’  
                Government directly. Accordingly in 1993 ll'  
                a letter to the Minister of Foreign Affain °f  i   l
                try, in which after indignantly expressiU8 N' 
                the conduct of the French Government, in th0 ____ 
                of this large sum and the erection of fortrel|°° I
                Concessions he re ° d h th mainde!'°f ‘M
                , qutre t at e re _ M
                millions should be immediately   inw bl' °'°
                 _s
                l 1
                Denial;  

              </ab> 
          </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
