<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SLM ???</title>
                <respStmt>
    		<resp>Compiled by</resp>
				<name>
				Jordan
				</name>
		</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>???</publisher>
                <pubPlace>???</pubPlace>
                <date>???</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>
		???
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
        <p>
        </p>
    <p><lb n="0"/>SOUTHERN LITERARY MESSENGER. 3</p>
<p><lb n="1"/>and that thehe French claimants should then submit their
<lb n="2"/>demands to him for adjustment.</p>
<lb n="3"/><p>No notice having been taken of the Dey’s letter, the
<lb n="4"/>Algerine cruisers began to search French vessels in a
<lb n="5"/>manner contrary to the terms of existing treaties, and
<lb n="6"/>to plunder those of the Papal States which were by a
<lb n="7"/>Convention to be respected as French. Besides these
<lb n="8"/>acts of violence the Dey shortly after issued a procla-
<lb n="9"/>mation declaring that all nations would be permitted
<lb n="10"/>on the same terms to fish for coral near the coasts of his
<lb n="11"/>Regency. M. Deval complained of these proceedings
<lb n="12"/>at a public audience on the 27th of April, 1827;
<lb n="13"/>Hussein in reply haughtily declared that he had been
<lb n="14"/>.provoked to them by the bad faith of the French,
<lb n="15"/>and that he should no longer allow them to have a
<lb n="16"/>cannon in his territories, nor to enjoy a single peculiar
<lb n="17"/>privilege; he then demanded why his letter to the
<lb n="18"/>French Ministry had not been answered, and when
<lb n="19"/>,M. Deval stated that his Government could only com-
<lb n="20"/>municate with that of Algiers through himself, he was
<lb n="21"/>so much enraged that he seized a large fan from one of
<lb n="22"/>the attendants, with which he struck the representative
<lb n="23"/>of France several times before he could leave the apart-
<lb n="24"/>°ment</p>
            <p>As soon as the French Government was informed
<lb n="25"/>of this outrage, a schooner was despatched to Algiers
<lb n="26"/>with orders to M. Deval to quit the place instantly; a
<lb n="27"/>squadron was also sent in the same direction, under
<lb n="28"/>the command of Commodore Collet who was charged
<lb n="29"/>to require satisfaction from the Dey. The schooner
<lb n="30"/>arrived in Algeers on the llth of June, and M. Deval
<lb n="31"/>embarked in her on the same day, together with the
<lb n="32"/>other French subjects resident in the place, leaving the
<lb n="33"/>affairs of his office under the care of the Sardinian
<lb n="34"/>Consul. At the entrance of the bay the schooner met
<lb n="35"/>the French squadron, consisting of a ship of the line,
<lb n="37"/>two frigates and a corvette; M. Deval then joined the
<lb n="38"/>Commodore, and after consultation between them as to
<lb n="39"/>the nature and mode of the reparation to be demanded,
<lb n="40"/>the schooner was sent back to Algiers with a note con-
<lb n="41"/>taining what was declared to be the ultimatum of the
<lb n="42"/>French Government. This note was presented to Hus-
<lb n="43"/>sein on the l4th; in it the Dey was required to apolo-
<lb n="44"/>gize for the offence committed against the dignity of
<lb n="45"/>France by the insult to its representative; and in
<lb n="46"/>order to make the apology the more striking and com-
<lb n="47"/>plete, it was to be delivered on board the Commodore’s
<lb n="48"/>ship, by the Minister of Marine, in the presence of M.
<lb n="49"/>Deval, and of all the foreign Consuls resident in Al-
<lb n="50"/>giers, whose attendance was to be requested; the
<lb n="51"/>French flag was then to be displayed on the Casauba
<lb n="52"/>and principal forts, and M. Deval was to receive a sa-
<lb n="53"/>lute of one hundred and ten guns.</p>
<lb n="54"/><p>The policy as well as the generosity of requiring
<lb n="55"/>such humiliating concessions from the Government of
<lb n="56"/>any country, may be questioned, but it is certainly
<lb n="57"/>hazardous to make the demand unless it be accompa-
<lb n="58"/>nied by the display of a force calculated to insure im-
<lb n="59"/>mediate compliance. Decatur indeed with a force per-
<lb n="60"/>haps inferior to that of Collet, propounded terms to Omar
<lb n="61"/>Dey in 1815, which were really much more onerous to
<lb n="62"/>Algiers than those offered on the present occasion by
<lb n="63"/>the French; they were accepted, and it is therefore
<lb n="64"/>needless to inquired what would have been his course in
<lb n="65"/>the other alternative. Collet was not so fortunate; his
<lb n="66"/>demands were rejected with scorn and defiance by Hus-
<lb n="67"/>sein, who added that if the Commodore did not within
<lb n="68"/>twenty-four hours land and treat with him on the sub-
<lb n="69"/>jects in dispute between the two nations, he should
<lb n="70"/>consider himself at war with France. The French
<lb n="71"/>Commander did not think proper to comply with this
<lb n="72"/>invitation, and declared the place in a state of blockade,
<lb n="73"/>under the expectation probably that the distress pro-
<lb n="74"/>duced by such a measure, might occasion discontent and
<lb n="75"/>commotions which would either oblige the Dey to lower
<lb n="76"/>his tone, or lead to the destruction of so refractory an ene-
<lb n="77"/>my. Recollecting however what had occurred at Bona in
<lb n="78"/>May 1816, he adopted the precaution of sending vessels
<lb n="79"/>to the various establishments in the Concessions, in order
<lb n="80"/>to bring away the Europeans who were there, under
<lb n="81"/>the protection of the French flag; these vessels succeed-
<lb n="82"/>ed in rescuing the people, who were transported to Cor-
<lb n="83"/>sica, but their dwellings and magazines were rifled by
<lb n="84"/>the Bey of the Province, who had just received orders
<lb n="85"/>to that effect, and the fortifications at Calle were en-
<lb n="86"/>tirely destroyed.</p>
<lb n="87"/><p>The preceding account ofthe circumstances which led
<lb n="88"/>to the war between France and Algiers, will be found
<lb n="89"/>by comparison to vary considerably from those given
<lb n="90"/>by the French historical writers, and to be defective and
<lb n="91"/>unsatisfactory with regard to several important particu-
<lb n="92"/>lars, which are stated by them with great apparent
<lb n="93"/>clearness and confidence. To these objections, only
<lb n="94"/>general replies can be made; this account has been
<lb n="95"/>drawn entirely from original sources, and where they
<lb n="96"/>failed to supply the requisite information, silence has
<lb n="97"/>been preferred to the introduction of statements on
<lb n="98"/>doubtful authority. The only publications on the sub-
<lb n="99"/>ject which may be termed ofiicial, are the declarations
<lb n="100"/>of the French Ministers contained in the Reports of the
<lb n="101"/>Debates in the Legislative Chambers, and the articles
<lb n="102"/>on the subject in question inserted from time to time in
<lb n="103"/>the Moniteur, the avowed organ of the Government.
<lb n="104"/>From the Algerines we have nothing. The conventions
<lb n="105"/>of which the alleged non-fulfilment occasioned this rup-
<lb n="106"/>ture have been withheld by the French Ministry; no
<lb n="107"/>account has been given of the claims against Algiers
<lb n="108"/>brought before the French Courts, of the causes which
<lb n="109"/>retarded the decisions respecting them, of the amount
<lb n="110"/>demanded or awarded; without precise information as
<lb n="111"/>to these particulars, it is impossible to form a correct
<lb n="112"/>judgment of the case. This silence and the vagueness
<lb n="113"/>and reserve so apparent in the communications of the
<lb n="114"/>French Govemment, on the subject, are certainly calcu-
<lb n="115"/>lated to create suspicions, as to its sincerity in main-
<lb n="116"/>taining its engagements, and these suspicions are in-
<lb n="117"/>creased by an examination of its conduct throughout the
<lb n="118"/>whole affair.</p>
<lb n="119"/><p>It would be incompatible with the character or plan
<lb n="120"/>of these Sketches, to give a review of the proceed-
<lb n="121"/>ings of the French Government; the impression pro-
<lb n="122"/>duced on the mind of the author, by a diligent study of
<lb n="123"/>the case, is that the parties in the dispute mistrusted
<lb n="124"/>the intentions of each other. The French were anxious
<lb n="125"/>to make permanent establishments on the coast of
<lb n="126"/>Northern Africa, which Hussein who had much mone
<lb n="127"/>definite ideas of policy than perhaps any of his prede-
<lb n="128"/>cessors, determined from the commencement of his reign
<lb n="129"/>to oppose; before resorting to violent measures how.
<lb n="130"/>ever, he wished to secure the payment of the large debt
<lb n="131"/>
</p></body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
