<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
       <title>
        [Original Title]- electronic transcription
       </title>
       <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
       <principal>J. Gerald Kennedy</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
         <publisher>Louisiana State University</publisher>
         <pubPlace>Baton Rouge, LA</pubPlace>
         <date>2014</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Southern Literary Messenger, vol 12, 1835</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="1"/>
                <lb n="0"/><head>SOUTHERN LITERARY MESSENGER.</head>
                <lb n="1"/><head>Vol. II RICHMOND, DECEMBER, 1835. No. 1.</head>
                <lb n="2"/><head>T.W. White, PROPRIETOR</head>
                <lb n="4"/><head>FIVE DOLLARS PER ANNUM</head>
                <lb n="5"/> 
                <div type="article">
                    <author ref="slm183610pp1lsuv_publishers_note">unknown</author>
                <lb n="6"/><head>PUBLISHER’S NOTICE</head>
                <p><lb n="7"/>The gentleman, referred to in the ninth number
                <lb n="8"/>of the Messenger, as filling its editorial chair, retired
                <lb n="9"/>thence with the eleventh number; and the intellectual
                <lb n="10"/>odepartment of the paper is now under the conduct
                <lb n="11"/>of the Proprietor, assisted by a gentleman of distin-
                <lb n="12"/>guished literary talents. Thus seconded, he is sanguine
                <lb n="13"/>in the hope of rendering the second volume which the
                <lb n="14"/>present number commences, at least as deserving of
                <lb n="15"/>support as the former was: nay, if he reads aright the
                <lb n="16"/>°tokens which are given him of the future, it teems with
                <lb n="17"/>event richer banquets for his readers, than they have
                <lb n="18"/>hitherto enjoyed at his board.</p>
                <lb n="19"/><p>Some of the contributors, whose effusions have re-
                <lb n="20"/>ceived the largest share of praise from critics, and
                <lb n="21"/>(what is better still) have been read with most pleasure
                <lb n="22"/>by that larger, unsophisticated class, whom Sterne loved
                <lb n="23"/>for reading, and being pleased “they knew not why,
                <lb n="24"/>and care not wherefore”--may be expected to continue
                <lb n="25"/>their favors. Among these, we hope to be pardoned
                <lb n="26"/>for singling out the name of <persName ref="http://lccn.loc.gov/n79029745">Mr. EDGAR A. Poe</persName>; not
                <lb n="27"/>with design to make any invidious distinction, but
                <lb n="28"/>because such a mention of him finds numberless prece-
                <lb n="29"/>dents in the journals on every side,which have rung
                <lb n="30"/>the praises of his uniquely original vein of imagination,
                <lb n="31"/>and of humorous, delicate satire. We wish that deco-
                <lb n="32"/>rum did not forbid our specifying other names also,
                <lb n="33"/>which would afford ample guarantee for the fulfilment
                <lb n="34"/>of larger promises than ours: but it may not be; and of
                <lb n="35"/>our other contributors, all we can say is-“by their
                <lb n="36"/>fruits ye shall know them.”</p>
                <lb n="37"/><p>It is part of our present plan, to insert all original
                <lb n="38"/>:communications as editorial; that is, simply to omit the
                <lb n="39"/>words "For the Southern Literary Messenger” at the
                <lb n="40"/>head of such articles:--unless the contributor shall es-
                <lb n="41"/>pecially desire to have that caption prefixed, or there be
                <lb n="42"/>something which requires it in the nature of the article
                <lb n="43"/>itself. Selected articles, of course, will bear some appro-
                <lb n="44"/>priate token of their origin.</p>
                <lb n="45"/><p>With this brief salutation to patrons and readers, we
                <lb n="46"/>gird up ourselves for entering upon the work of another
                <lb n="47"/>year, with zeal and energy increased, by the recollec-
                <lb n="48"/>tion of kindness, and by the hopes of still greater suc-
                <lb n="49"/>cess</p>
                <lb n="50"/> <p>line</p>
                </div>
                <div type="article">
                <author ref="slm183610pp1lsuv_sketches_of_the_history">unknown</author>
                <lb n="51"/><head>SKETCHES OF THE HISTORY</head>
                <lb n="52"/><p>And Present Condition of Tripoli, with some ac-</p>
                <lb n="53"/><p>counts of the other Barbary States</p>
                <lb n="54"/>
                <lb n="55"/><p>NO. IX.-(Contlnued.)</p>
                <lb n="56"/><p>About this period commenced those differences be-
                <lb n="57"/>tween France and the Algerine Government, which led
                <lb n="58"/>to the overthrow of the latter, and the establishment of
                <lb n="59"/>the French in Northern Africa; the circumstances
                <lb n="60"/>which occasioned the dispute were however of much
                <lb n="61"/>older date.</p>
                <p>|Between 1793 and 1798 the French Government on
                <lb n="62"/>several occasions obtained from the Dey and merchants
                <lb n="63"/>of <placeName ref="http://sws.geonames.org/1023343/about.rdf">Algiers</placeName>, large quantities of grain on credit, for the
                <lb n="64"/>subsistence of its armies in Italy, and the supply of the
                <lb n="65"/>Southern Department where a great scarcity then pre-
                <lb n="66"/>vailed. The creditors endeavored to have their claims
                <lb n="67"/>on this account satisfied by the Directory, but that in-
                <lb n="68"/>capable and rapacious Government had neither the
                <lb n="69"/>principle to admit, nor the ability to discharge such de-
                <lb n="70"/>mands; every species of chicanery was in consequence
                <lb n="71"/>employed by it in evading them, until the rupture with
                <lb n="72"/>Turkey produced by the expedition to Egypt placing
                <lb n="73"/>the Barbary States either really or apparently at war
                <lb n="74"/>with the French Republic, a pretext was thus afforded
                <lb n="75"/>for deferring their settlement indefinitely. Under the
                <lb n="76"/>Consular regime however, a treaty of peace was con-
                <lb n="77"/>cluded with Algiers on the 17th of December 1801,
                <lb n="78"/>by the thirteenth article of which, the Government
                <lb n="79"/>of each State engaged to cause payment to be made
                <lb n="80"/>of all debts due by itself or its subjects to the Gov-
                <lb n="81"/>ernment or subjects of the other; the former political
                <lb n="82"/>and commercial relations between the two countries
                <lb n="83"/>were re-established, and the Dey restored to France
                <lb n="84"/>the territories and privileges called the African Con-
                <lb n="85"/>cessions, which had been seized by him on the break-
                <lb n="86"/>ing out of the war. This treaty was ratined by the
                <lb n="87"/>Dey on the 5th of April 1802, and after examination
                <lb n="88"/>of the claims on both sides, the French Govern-
                <lb n="89"/>ment acknowledged itself debtor for a large amount to
                <lb n="90"/>the Jewish mercantile house of Bacri and Busnach of
                <lb n="91"/>Algiers, as representing the African creditors. Of the
                <lb n="92"/>sum thus acknowledged to be due, only a very small
                <lb n="93"/>portion was paid, and the Dey Hadji Ali seeing no
                <lb n="94"/>other means of obtaining the remainder, in 1809 seized
                <lb n="95"/>upon the Concessions; they were however of little value
                <lb n="96"/>to France at that time, when her flag was never seen in
                <lb n="97"/>the Mediterranean, and their confiscation merely served
                <lb n="98"/>as a pretext for withholding farther payment. In 1813,
                <lb n="99"/>when the star of Napoleon began to wane, and he
                <lb n="100"/>found it necessary to assume at least the appearance of
                <lb n="101"/>honesty, he declared that measures would be taken for
                <lb n="102"/>the adjustment of the Algerine claims; but he fell
                <lb n="103"/>without redeeming his promise, and on the distribution
                <lb n="104"/>of his spoils, the Jewish merchants had not interest
                <lb n="105"/>enough to obtain their rightful portion, which amounted
                <lb n="106"/>to fourteen millions of francs.</p>
                <lb n="107"/><p>Upon the return of the Bourbons to the throne of
                <lb n="108"/>France, the government of that country became desirous
                <lb n="109"/>to renew its former intercourse with the Barbary States,
                <lb n="110"/>and to regain its ancient establishments and privileges
                <lb n="111"/>in their territories, which were considered important
                <lb n="112"/>from political as well as commercial motives. For this
                <lb n="113"/>purpose, M. Deval a person who was educated in the
                <lb n="114"/>East and had been long attached to the French Em-
                <lb n="115"/>bassy at Constantinople, was appointed Consul General
                <lb n="116"/>of France in Barbary, and sent to Algiers with powers
                <lb n="117"/>to negotiate. The first result of this mission, was a
                <lb n="118"/>convention which has never been ofticially published;
                <lb n="119"/>however in consequence of it the African Concessions
                <lb n="120"/>were restored to France, together with the exclusive
                <lb n="121"/>right of fishing for coral on the coasts in their vicinity
                <lb n="122"/>Vol.. II.-1</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <!-- page 2 follows, etc -->
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
